[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
教授: 接下来我要解开
PROFESSOR: Well, there's one bit of mystery left,
目前仅剩的谜团
which I'd like to get rid of right now.
我们能毫无顾虑地用CONS
And that's that we've been blithely doing things like cons
就好像空间足够多一样
assuming there's always another one.
我们总是在使用
That we've been doing these things like
CAR和CDR
car-ing and cdr-ing
并假设知道它们是如何实现的
and assuming that we had some idea how this can be done.
事实上
Now indeed
我们认为它等同于过程
we said that that's equivalent to having procedures.
但这没有真正解决问题
OK? But that doesn't really solve the problem,
因为过程依赖各种复杂的机制
because the procedure need all sorts of complicated mechanisms
需要诸如环境结构之类的东西
like environment structures
才能运行起来
and things like that to work.
而归根结底它们也是
And those were ultimately made out of conses
由CONS之类的东西构成的
in the model that we had,
这的确没有解决问题
so that really doesn't solve the problem.
目前的问题是
Now the problem here is
粘合这些数据结构的是什么东西？
is the glue the data structure's made out of.
它可能是怎样的一个东西?
What kind of possible thing could it be?
我们已经见过了一台机器
OK? We've been showing you things like a machine,
一台计算机具有一个控制器
a computer that has a controller,
和一些寄存器
and some registers,
还可能有一个栈
and maybe a stack.
但是我们还没提到一些东西
And we haven't said anything about,
例如 大内存
for example, larger memory.
我先 现在是时候讨论它们了
And I think that's what we have to worry about right now.
#TBD
But just to make it perfectly clear that this is an inessential,
purely implementational thing,
让我举个例子
I'd like to show you, for example,
如何用数字来表示这些东西
how you can do it all with the numbers.
有个比较简单的方法
That's an easy one.
一位著名的逻辑学家 哥德尔
Famous fellow by the name of Godel,
在20世纪30年代末
a logician at the end of the 1930s,
发明了一个很巧妙的方法
invented a very clever way
能够把复杂的表达式
of encoding the complicated expressions
表示成数字
as numbers.
例如
For example--
我不会精确描述哥德尔的方法是怎样的
I'm not saying exactly what Godel's scheme is,
因为他没有使用CONS之类的术语
because he didn't use words like cons.
他使用了其它的组合手段
He had other kinds of
来编码表达式
of ways of combining to make expressions.
他的思路是
But he said,
用不同数字分别代表每个代数式
I'm going to assign a number to every algebraic expression.
通过用这些数字进行一些数学运算 #TBD
And the way I'm going to manufacture these numbers
来把这些部分组合起来
is by combining the numbers of the parts.
举例来说
So for example,
我们在创造世界的时候
what we were doing our world,
如果用数字
we could say that if objects
来表示对象
are represented by numbers,
那么(CONS X Y)
then cons of x and y
就可以表示为
could be represented by, could be represented by
2的X次幂乘3的Y次幂
2 to the x times 2 to the y.
因为这样我们还能取出它的每一部分
Because then we could extract the parts.
举例来说
We could say, for example,
(CAR X)
that then car of, say, x
就是X中因数2的个数
is the number of factors of 2 in x.
当然(CDR X)是一样的
OK? And of course cdr is the same thing.
它就X中因数3的个数
It's the number of factors of 3 in x.
这是个非常合理的方案
Now this is a perfectly reasonable scheme,
只不过就是
except for the fact that
数字的位数会急剧地增大
the numbers rapidly get to be much larger in number of digits
甚至比宇宙中的粒子还多
than the number of protons in the universe.
所以除了在理论中
So there's no easy way to use this scheme
没有实现这种方案的好办法
other than the theoretical one.
另一方面
On the other hand,
也有其它的表示方式
there are other ways of representing these things.
我们把它们表示为
We have been thinking in terms
一些小盒子
of little boxes, boxes.
我们把CONS结构
We've been thinking about our cons structures
想象为这样的东西
as looking sort of like this.
它们是里面装着东西的小隔间
They're little pigeon holes with things in them.
这些格子组成一个树
And of course we arrange them in little trees.
我希望半导体制造商
I wish that the semiconductor manufacturers
能够提供适配这样需求的芯片
would supply me with something appropriate for this,
但事实上
but actually
他们提供给我的却是
what they do supply me with
线性的内存
is a linear memory.
内存是一串小隔间
Memory is sort of a big pile of pigeonholes,
像这样的小隔间
pigeonholes like this.
每个小隔间里可以保存确定大小的对象
Each of which can hold a certain sized object,
一个尺寸固定的对象
a fixed size object.
例如
So, for example,
一个含25个元素的表
a complicated list with 25 elements
就放不进这里
won't fit in one of these.
然而 它们每一个都是由地址索引的
However, each of these is indexed by an address.
因此它们的地址可能是
So the address might be
这里是0
zero here,
这里是1
one here,
这里是2
two here,
这里是3
three here,
以此类推
and so on.
这里写的数字并不重要
That we write these down as numbers is unimportant.
重要的是 它们不重复
What matters is that they're distinct
有了它们就能找到下一个在哪
as a way to get to the next one.
在其中每一个小隔间里面
And inside of each of these,
我们可以把东西放进去
we can stuff something into these pigeonholes.
对于没有造过计算机的我们来说
That's what memory is like,
内存就是这样子的
for those of you who haven't built a computer.
现在
Now.
现在的问题是
Now the problem is
如何用这样的结构
how are we going to impose on this type of structure,
来实现这个树形结构
this nice tree structure.
其实并不难
Well it's not very hard,
已经有大量的方案来做这个了
and there have been numerous schemes involved in this.
最重要的一个方案是
The most important one is to say,
假设半导体生产厂
well assuming that the semiconductor manufacturer allows me to arrange
允许我们的其中一个小隔间足够大
my memory so that one of these pigeonholes is big enough
能够装得下另一个的地址
to hold the address of another
另一个未使用的小隔间的地址
I haven't made.
事实上它需要更大一点
Now it actually has to be a little bit bigger
因为我还要存一些信息在里面
because I have to also install or store some information
它标示了这里面是什么东西
as to a tag which describes the kind of thing that's there.
我们过一会能看到
And we'll see that in a second.
如果半导体生产厂没这么良心
And of course if the semiconductor manufacturer doesn't arrange it so I can do that,
我就需要用一些机智的方式
then of course I can, with some cleverness,
把它们组合起来以供使用
arrange combinations of these to fit together in that way.
我们想象一下
So we're going to have to imagine
把这个复杂的树形结构
imposing this complicated tree structure
塞进线性内存里
on our nice linear memory.
#TBD
If we look at the first still store,
我们发现了一个传统的实现方案
we see a classic scheme for doing that.
它是把Lisp结构
It's a standard way of representing Lisp structures
放入线性内存的基本方式
in a linear memory.
我们把这块内存
What we do is we divide this memory
分为两部分
into two parts.
一个叫the-cars的数组
An array called the cars,
一个叫the-cdrs的数组
and an array called the cdrs.
它是不是顺序地址
Now whether those happen to be sequential addresses or whatever,
其实并不重要
it's not important.
这是实现细节了
That's somebody's implementation details.
但有两个数组
But there are two arrays here.
一维数组是由顺序的下标索引的
Linear arrays indexed by sequential indices like this.
每个小隔间里存的
What is stored in each of these pigeonholes
是一个带类型的对象
is a typed object.
这里是
And what we have here
以字母p开头
are types which begin with letters like p,
表示序对
standing for a pair.
以n开头 表示数字
Or n, standing for a number.
e开头 表示空列表
Or e, standing for an empty list.
以及列表的结尾
The end of the list.
如果我们想表示这样一个对象
And so if we wish to represent an object like this,
列表由(1 2)开始
the list beginning with 1, 2
3和4是它的第二和第三个元素
and then having a 3 and a 4 as its second and third elements.
它第一个部分是一个包含了列表的列表
A list containing a list as its first part
后面接着是两个数字
and then two numbers
分别为第二和第三部分
as a second and third parts.
现在我们用盒子和指针表示法来描绘它
Then of course we draw it sort of like this these days, in box-and-pointer notation.
你能发现
And you see,
有三个格子里是CAR指针
these are the three cells that have as their car pointer
对象是(1 2)或3或4
the object which is either 1, 2 or 3 or 4.
当然这个(1 2)
And then of course the 1, 2,
即整个结构的CAR
the car of this entire structure,
就是一个包含子列表的子结构
is itself a substructure which contains a sublist like that.
我要做的是
What I'm about to do
就是按照下标把它们放进去
is put down places which are-- I'm going to assign indices.
像这里的1
Like this 1, over here,
代表了这个格子的下标
represents the index of this cell.
这里的指针
But that pointer that we see here
是对the-cars和the-cdrs里的小隔间的引用
is a reference to the pair of pigeonholes in the cars and the cdrs
在线性内存里
that are labeled by 1
被标记为1
in my linear memory down here.
如果我想把这个结构塞进线性内存中
So if I wish to impose this structure on my linear memory,
要做的是
what I do is I say, oh yes,
把它放进格子1中
why don't we drop this into cell 1?
我拿了个1
I pick one.
这是个1
There's 1.
这是它的CAR
And that says that its car,
我要把它赋值给一个序对
I'm going to assign it to be a pair.
这个序对
It's a pair,
序号是5
which is in index 5.
它的CDR
And the cdr,
就是这个
which is this one over here,
它是个序对
is a pair
我会把它放到2的位置
which I'm going to stick into place 2.
即p2
p2.
我们看p2
And take a look at p2.
p2的CAR
Oh yes, well p2 is a thing
是数字3
whose car is the number 3,
如你所见 n3
so as you see, an n3.
它的CDR
And whose cdr, over here,
是一个序对
is a pair,
在位置4
which lives in place 4.
这就是p4
So that's what this p4 is.
p4是一个数字
p4 is a number
它的值是4 存在CDR中
whose value is 4 in its car
它的CDR
and whose cdr
是个空列表 在这儿
is an empty list right there.
这就结束了
And that ends it.
这就是在线性内存中
So this is the traditional way of representing
表示二叉树的传统方式
this kind of binary tree in a linear memory.
那么 下一个问题是
Now the next question, of course,
我们可能担心如何实现
that we might want to worry about is just a little bit of implementation.
这意味着当我写下一个对a赋值的过程
That means that when I write procedures of the form assigned a,
#TBD
[UNINTELLIGIBLE] procedures-- lines of register machine code of the form assigned a, the car of [UNINTELLIGIBLE] b,
我实际上想做的是
what I really mean
定位这些元素
is addressing these elements.
我们会把它当作一个缩写
And so we're going to think of that as a abbreviation for it.
当然 为了把它们写下来
Now of course in order to write that down
我要引入一种叫作向量的结构
I'm going to introduce some sort of a structure called a vector.
我们得有一种东西用来引用向量
And we're going to have something which will reference a vector,
这样我们就能把它写下来
just so we can write it down.
它叫向量vector
Which takes the name of the vector,
我觉得这个名字起得不太靠谱
or the-- I don't think that name is the right word.
它接受vector和index两个参数
Which takes the vector and the index,
#TBD
and I have to have a way of setting one of those with something called a vector set,
我不太在意
I don't really care.
举个例子
But let's look, for example,
在这种实现中
at then that kind of implementation
CAR和CDR是什么样子的
of car and cdr.
如果我有一个寄存器b
So for example if I happen to have a register b,
它存了一个序对的下标
which contains the type index of a pair,
即它是指向一个序对的指针
and therefore it is the pointer to a pair,
我可以取它的CAR
then I could take the car of that and
存到寄存器a里面
if I-- write this down-- I might put that in register a.
事实上它是
What that really is is a representation of
#TBD
the assign to a,
the value of vector reffing-- or array indexing, if you will-- or something,
#TBD
the cars object-- whatever that is-- with the index, b.
与CDR类似
And similarly for cdr.
我们可以用同样的方式
And we can do the same thing
来对数据结构赋值
for assignment to data structures,
如果我们需要这么做的话
If we need to do that sort of things at all.
构建这个并不太难
It's not too hard to build that.
下一个问题是
Well now the next question is
我们如何分配它们
how are we going to do allocation.
我说过很多次 我需要一个CONS
And every so often I say I want a cons.
当然 CONS并没有长在树上
Now conses don't grow on trees.
或许它们应该那样
Or maybe they should.
我需要某种获得下一个的方法
But I have to have some way of getting the next one.
我需要某种方案
I have to have some idea of
当内存不再使用的时候
if their memory is unused
我可以重新分配它们
that I might want to allocate from.
有很多方案可以实现这一点
And there are many schemes for doing this.
我给你看这这个东西是不必要的
And the particular thing I'm showing you right now is not essential.
然而它很方便
However it's convenient
并且被实现很多次了
and has been done many times.
其中一种被称为自由表分配方案
One scheme's was called the free list allocation scheme.
它的意思就是
What that means is
世界上所有的空闲内存
that all of the free memory that there is in the world
都连在一个链表中
is linked together in a linked list,
就像其他东西一样
just like all the other stuff.
每当你需要一个新的格子
And whenever you need a free cell
来进行CONS的时候
to make a new cons,
你把第一个拿去用
you grab the first one
让它的CDR作为新的自由表
make the free list be the cdr of it,
然后分配它
and then allocate that.
就像这样
And so what that looks like is something like this.
我们的自由表从6开始
Here we have the free list starting in 6.
它是一个指向8的指针
And what that is is a pointer-off to say 8.
它表示
So what it says is,
当前这个是空闲的
this one is free
下一个在8
and the next one is an 8.
这个是空闲的
This one is free
下一个在3
and the next one is in 3,
下一个是空闲的
the next one that's free.
这个是空闲的
That one's free
下一个在0
and the next one is in 0.
这个是空闲的
That one's free
下一个在15
and the next one's in 15.
以此类推
Something like that.
我们可以想象有这样的结构
We can imagine having such a structure.
一旦我们有了这样的机制
Given that we have something like that,
那么当你需要空间的时候
then it's possible to
就能获取一个
just get one when you need it.
对于进行CONS的程序
And so a program for doing cons,
这就是CONS的程序会是什么样子
this is what cons might turn into.
把B和C进行CONS之后的值
To assign to a register A the result of cons-ing,
赋值给A寄存器
a B onto C,
结果包括B和C
the value in this containing B and the value containing C,
我们要做的是使用自由表前面的第一个
what we have to do is get the current [? type ?] ahead of the freelist,
让它的CDR成为新的自由表
make the free list be its cdr.
我们要把CAR修改为
Then we have to change the cars to be the thing we're
#TBD
making up to be in A to be the B, the thing in B.
我们还要把CDR改为#TBD
And we have to make change the cdrs of the thing that's in A to be C.
#TBD
And then what we have in A is the right new frob, whatever it is.
这就是我们要的对象
The object that we want.
我之前告诉过你们
Now there's a little bit of
这里撒了个谎
a cheat here that I haven't told you about,
#TBD
which is somewhere around here I haven't set that
I've the type of the thing that I'm cons-ing up to be a pair, and I ought to.
#TBD
So there should be some sort of bits here are being set,
我只是还没把它写下来
and I just haven't written that down.
#TBD
We could have arranged it, of course, for the free lift to be made out of pairs.
因此这是没问题的
And so then there's no problem with that.
#TBD
But that sort of-- again, an inessential detail in a way
some particular programmer or architect or whatever might manufacture his machine or Lisp system.
例如
So for example,
看这个
just looking at this,
假设我们要为
to allocate
这个之前见过的数据结构分配空间
given that I had already the structure that you saw before,
假设我要分配一个新单元
supposing I wanted to allocate a new cell,
把列表(1 1 2)
which is going to be representation of list one, one, two,
放到(1 2)为CAR这个列表的前面
where already one two was the car of the list we were playing with before.
这不怎么难
Well that's not so hard.
#TBD
I stored that one and one,
那么p1表示的就是它
so p1 one is the representation of this.
这个是p5
This is p5.
它是应该是这个的CDR
That's going to be the cdr of this.
现在我们想用掉一些自由表
Now we're going to pull something off the free list,
记住自由表从6开始
but remember the free list started at six.
分配之后的新自由表指针是8
The new free list after this allocation is eight,
一个从8开始的自由表
a free list beginning at eight.
当然
And of course
现在6里面是数字1
in six now we have a number one,
就是我们想要的
which is what we wanted,
它的CDR是在位置5的序对
with its cdr being the pair starting in location five.
没费多少力气
And that's no big deal.
这里依然存在的一个问题是
So the only problem really remaining here is,
我们没有无限大的内存
well, I don't have an infinitely large memory.
如果它需要花费一些时间
If I do this for a little while,
例如 假设进行一次CONS花费1微秒
say, for example, supposing it takes me a microsecond to do a cons,
我们要进行一百万次CONS
and I have a million cons memory
那么我就要消耗1秒钟的时间
then I'm only going to run out in a second,
这就很糟糕了
and that's pretty bad.
如何预防这样的灾难
So what we do to prevent that disaster,
生态灾难
that ecological disaster,
在提问环节之后我们再继续讨论
talk about right after questions.
有人要提问吗?
Are there any questions?
请讲
Yes.
学生: 在环境图表中
AUDIENCE: In the environment diagrams that we were drawing
我们画了过程体
we would use the body of procedures,
#TBD
and you would eventually wind up with things that were no longer useful in that structure.
它是如何表示的
How is that represented?
教授: 这其实是两个问题
PROFESSOR: There's two problems here.
第一个问题是
One you were asking
材料没用了
is that material becomes useless.
我们稍后就会讲
We'll talk about that in a second.
如何预防生态灾难
That has to do with how to prevent ecological disasters.
如果我制造了一堆垃圾
If I make a lot of garbage
我需要自己清理掉
I have to somehow be able to clean up after myself.
我们一会儿就要讲
And we'll talk about that in a second.
第二个问题
The other question you're asking
你问的是如何表示环境
is how you represent the environments, I think.
学生: 对
AUDIENCE: Yes.
教授: 好
PROFESSOR: OK.
环境结构能够以任意的方式表示
And the environment structures can be represented in arbitrary ways.
有很多种表示方式
There are lots of them.
我的意思是 我这里只教你了列表格子的表示方式
I mean, here I'm just telling you about list cells.
当然 每个真实的系统
Of course every real system
都有任意长度的向量
has vectors of arbitrary length
也有长度的向量表示#TBD
as well as the vectors of length, too, which represent list cells.
在一个专业的Lisp系统中
And the environment structures that one uses in a
环境结构是用
professionally written Lisp system
向量表示的
tend to be vectors
其中包含了约等于参数数量的元素
which contain a number of elements approximately
--比它稍微多一点
equal to the number of arguments-- a little bit more
因为你需要#TBD
because you need certain glue.
记住环境是在框架里的
So remember, the environment is in a frame.
框架是应用过程时被构建出来的
The frames are constructed by applying a procedure.
#TBD
In doing so, an allocation is made of
a place which is the number of arguments long plus [? unglue ?]
#TBD
that gets linked into a chain.
在这个层次上 和ALGOL差不多
It's just like algol at that level.
还有其他问题吗?
There any other questions?
好
OK.
谢谢 我们休息一下
Thank you, and let's take a short break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
教授: 就像我刚才提到过的
PROFESSOR: Well, as I just said,
半导体厂商生产的计算机内存
computer memories supplied by the semiconductor manufacturers
容量是有限的
are finite.
这的确很可惜
And that's quite a pity.
可能并不永远是这样
It might not always be that way.
简单算一下
Just for a quick calculation,
你可以看到 如果内存的价格
you can see that it's possible that if memory's
继续保持当前的趋势的话
prices keep going at the rate they're going
如果你执行CONS的时候一直花费1微秒
that if you still took a microsecond second to do a cons,
那么 首先大家知道
then-- first of all,
pi乘10的7次方秒大约是一年
everybody should know that there's about pi times ten to the seventh seconds in a year.
那么就有
And so that would be
10的6次方乘10的7次方
ten to the seventh plus ten to the sixth
也就是10的13次方
is ten to the thirteenth.
那么在机器的一生中
So there's maybe ten to the fourteenth conses
就能有10的14次方个CONS
in the life of a machine.
如果你的机器上有10的14次方个字的内存
If there was ten to the fourteenth words of memory on your machine,
你永远不会用完
you'd never run out.
这并不是完全没有道理
And that's not completely unreasonable.
10的14次方不是个非常大的数字
Ten to the fourteenth is not a very large number.
我不觉觉得它是个很大的数字
I don't think it is.
但我喜欢在天文学领域进行比较
But then again I like to play with astronomy.
距离我们最近的星星至少有10的18次方厘米远
It's at least ten to the eighteenth centimeters between us and the nearest star.
我担心的是
But the thing I'm about to worry about is,
至少以现在的经济状况
at least in the current economic state of affairs,
10的14次方内存很贵
ten to the fourteenth pieces of memory is expensive.
因此我认为我们需要适应更小的内存
And so I suppose what we have to do is make do with much smaller memories.
一般来说
Now in general
我们需要有无限内存的错觉
we want to have an illusion of infinity.
我们需要整理它
All we need to do is arrange it
那么在我们需要内存的时候就能获得它
so that whenever you look, the thing is there.
这是个非常重要的想法
That's really an important idea.
人或者计算机只能存在有限的时间
A person or a computer lives only a finite amount of time
只能看有限的东西
and can only take a finite number of looks at something.
因此你只需要有限的东西
And so you really only need a finite amount of stuff.
只要你去整理它
But you have to arrange it
那么不管实际有多少
so no matter how much there is,
你要求这里有多少
how much you really claim there is,
当你去看的时候
there's always enough stuff
总有足够的东西
so that when you take a look, it's there.
因此你只需要有限的数量
And so you only need a finite amount.
我们看
But let's see.
我们之前提过一个问题
One problem is, as was brought up,
在很多情况下
that there are possible ways
我们制造了大量我们不需要的东西
that there is lots of stuff that we make that we don't need.
我们可以进行回收再利用
And we could recycle the material out of which its made.
举个例子
An example
事实上
is the fact that
当我们调用一个过程的时候
we're building environment structures,
都会构建环境结构
and we do so every time we call a procedure.
我们把它构建在一个环境框架中
We have built in it a environment frame.
环境框架不用存在很长时间
That environment frame doesn't necessarily have a very long lifetime.
它只在有用的时候才会存在
Its lifetime, meaning its usefulness,
可能只在调用过程的时候才会存在
may exist only over the invocation of the procedure.
如果过程把另一个过程
Or if the procedure exports another procedure
作为返回值返回
by returning it as a value
并且这个过程是在它的内部定义的
and that procedure is defined inside of it,
那么外层过程的框架的存活时间
well then the lifetime of the frame of the outer procedure still is
就是被返回的过程的存活时间
only the lifetime of the procedure which was exported.
最终
And so ultimately,
就会产生很多垃圾
a lot of that is garbage.
还有其他产生垃圾的方式
There are other ways of producing garbage as well.
用户产生垃圾
Users produce garbage.
举例来说
An example of
用户的垃圾是这样的东西
user garbage is something like this.
如果我们写个程序
If we write a program to, for example,
把两个列表连接到一起
append two lists together,
唯一的办法是
well one way to do it is
把第一个列表逆序塞到空列表中
to reverse the first list onto the empty list
把新列表逆序塞到第二个列表中
and reverse that onto the second list.
这并不是完成任务的很差的办法
Now that's not terribly bad way of doing it.
然而
And however,
程序所生成的中间结果
the intermediate result, which is the reversal of the first list
即第一个逆序的列表
as done by this program,
在它被复制回第二个列表之后
is never going to be accessed ever again
再也不会被用到了
after it's copied back on to the second.
它是个中间结果
It's an intermediate result.
它很难被找到
It's going to be hard to ever see
没有人能访问到它
how anybody would ever be able to access it.
事实上 它会消失掉
In fact, it will go away.
如果我们制造了大量这样的垃圾
Now if we make a lot of garbage like that,
我们应该被允许这样做
and we should be allowed to,
但应该有某些方法去回收这些垃圾
then there's got to be some way to reclaim that garbage.
我现在要告诉你
Well, what I'd like to tell you about now
一个非常聪明的技巧
is a very clever technique
Lisp系统可以证明一个小定理#TBD
whereby a Lisp system can prove a small theorem every so often on the [? forum, ?] the following piece of junk will never be accessed again.
它对将来的计算没有任何影响
It can have no affect on the future of the computation.
事实上 这基于一个很简单的想法
It's actually based on a very simple idea.
我们已经把计算机设计成这个样子
We've designed our computers to look sort of like this.
有一些数据路径
There's some data path,
保存了寄存器
which contains the registers.
有EXP, ENV和VAL之类的东西
There are things like exp, and env, and val, and so on.
这里有个叫STACK的东西
And there's one here called stack,
某种指向一个结构的东西
some sort which points off to a structure somewhere,
它是个栈
which is the stack.
我们过一会再研究它
And we'll worry about that in a second.
这有一些有限控制器
There's some finite controller,
有限状态机控制器
finite state machine controller.
这些控制信号通过这里
And there's some control signals that go this way and
谓词结果通过这里
predicate results that come this way,
这部分并不太有趣
not the interesting part.
这里有某种结构化的内存
There's some sort of structured memory,
我刚才给你讲过如何构建它
which I just told you how to make,
它可能包括一个栈
which may contain a stack.
我没有告诉你如何把东西构建成任意形状
I didn't tell you how to make things of arbitrary shape,
只有序对
only pairs.
但事实上
But in fact
你可以用一个大列表来模拟栈
with what I've told you can simulate a stack by a big list.
我没准备干这个
I don't plan to do that,
这不是个好办法
it's not a nice way to do it.
但是我们可以有这样一个东西
But we could have something like that.
这里有各种数据结构
We have all sorts of little data structures in here
它们通过有趣的方式互相连接
that are hooked together in funny ways.
它们和其他东西连接到一起
They connect to other things.
以此类推
And so on.
归根结底
And ultimately
这里的东西是指向这里的指针
things up there are pointers to these.
寄存器里的东西
The things that are in the registers
是指向Lisp结构内存的数据结构指针
are pointers off to the data structures that live in this Lisp structure memory.
#TBD
Now the truth of the matter is
机器的整个意识是在寄存器里的
that the entire consciousness of this machine is in these registers.
如果这个机器
There is no possible way that the machine,
构建得正确的话
if done correctly, if built correctly,
它无法访问Lisp结构内存中任何东西
can access anything in this Lisp structure memory
除了在Lisp结构内存中
unless the thing in that Lisp structure memory
与序列数据结构连接的寄存器
is connected by a sequence of data structures to the registers.
#TBD如果合法数据结构选择器
If it's accessible by legitimate data structure selectors
通过寄存器里保存的指针能够访问它
from the pointers that are stored in these registers.
类似数组引用
Things like array references, perhaps.
或者#TBD
Or cons cell references, cars and cdrs.
但我不能只讨论内存中的任意位置
But I can't just talk about a random place in this memory,
因为我找不到它
because I can't get to it.
#TBD
These are being arbitrary names I'm not allowed to count,
at least as I'm evaluating expressions.
如果是这样的话
If that's the case
就可以证明一个简单的理论
then there's a very simple theorem to be proved.
就是说
Which is,
#TBD
if I start with all lead pointers that are in all these registers
递归地取出
and recursively chase out,
把所有能访问到的东西做标记
marking all the places I can get to by selectors,
最终就能标记所有能访问的东西
then eventually I mark everything they can be gotten to.
任何未标记的都是垃圾
Anything which is not so marked is garbage
它们可以被回收
and can be recycled.
非常简单
Very simple.
不会影响未来的计算
Cannot affect the future of the computation.
看下这个特殊的例子
So let me show you that in a particular example.
#TBD
Now that means I'm going to have to append to my description of the list structure a mark.
在这里是一个Lisp结构化的内存
And so here, for example, is a Lisp structured memory.
在这块内存里是一个Lisp数据结构
And in this Lisp structured memory is a Lisp structure
我们把这个起始位置
beginning in a place I'm going to call--
称为根
this is the root.
它不必真是的根
Now it doesn't really have to have a root.
因为有很多这种东西 与寄存器类似
It could be a bunch of them, like all the registers.
但我可以#TBD
But I could cleverly arrange it
因此所有的寄存器 所有在旧寄存器里的东西
so all the registers, all the things that are in old registers
也应该放在这个根结构里
are also at the right moment put into this root structure,
然后我们有一个指针指向它
and then we've got one pointer to it.
我不是很在意
I don't really care.
思路是 我们要一直把东西用cons连接起来 直到我们的free list为空
So the idea is we're going to cons up stuff until our free list is empty.
我们用尽所有的空间
We've run out of things.
现在我们要证明这个理论
Now we're going to do this process of proving the theorem
#TBD
that a certain percentage of the memory has got crap in it.
然后我们要回收它
And then we're going to recycle that
构建一个新的树
to grow new trees,
这是对于垃圾基本处理方式
a standard use of such garbage.
那么我们要做什么呢?
So in any case, what do we have here?
从p5这个位置开始
Well we have some data structure which starts out over here
存了一些数据结构
in p5.
从1开始
and it will start at one
事实上 p5是一个CAR
And in fact it has a car in p5,
它的CDR在2这个位置
and its cdr is in two.
所有标记都是从0开始的
And all the marks start out at zero.
我们要开始标记了
Well let's start marking, just to play this game.
好
OK.
例如
So for example,
因为我可以从根访问到它
since I can access one from the root
我就标记一下
I will mark that.
让我标记一下
Let me mark it.
砰
Bang.
这个被标记了
That's marked.
因为这有个5
Now since I have a five here
所以我跑到了5
I can go to five
看 我要标记这个
and see, well I'll mark that.
砰
Bang.
这是个有用的东西
That's useful stuff.
但5的CAR是个数字
But five references as a number in its car,
我对标记数字不感兴趣
I'm not interested in marking numbers
但它的CDR是7
but its cdr is seven.
所以我可以标记它
So I can mark that.
砰
Bang.
7是一个空列表
Seven is the empty list,
#TBD
the only thing that references,
它的CAR是个数字
and it's got a number in its car.
对它不感兴趣
Not interesting.
让我们回到这里
Well now let's go back here.
我忘记了一些事情
I forgot about something.
Two.
换句话说 如果我看格子1
See in other words, if I'm looking at cell one,
格子1包括了一个2
cell one contains a two right over here.
一个到2的引用
A reference to two.
这意味着我应该标记2
That means I should go mark two.
砰
Bang.
2包括了一个到4的引用
Two contains a reference to four.
它的CAR是个数字
It's got a number in its car,
我对它不感兴趣
I'm not interested in that
所以我要标记它
so I'm going to go mark that.
4通过CAR引用了7
Four refers to seven through its car,
它的CDR是空的
and is empty in its cdr,
但由于我已经标记过了
but I've already marked that one
就不再次标记它了
so I don't have to mark it again.
这就是这个地方所有能够访问的结构
This is all the accessible structure from that place.
很简单的递归标记算法
Simple recursive mark algorithm.
这个算法有一些不足的地方
Now there are some unhappinesses about that algorithm,
我们稍后会说
and we can worry about that a second.
但基本上你能看到
But basically you'll see
所有没被标记的地方
that all the things that have not been marked
都是无用的
are places that are free,
可以回收
and I could recycle.
所以下一步就是
So the next stage after that is going to be
扫描整个内存
to scan through all of my memory,
寻找未被标记的东西
looking for things that are not marked.
每当遇到一个已标记的东西
Every time I come across a marked thing
就把标记去掉
I unmark it,
每当遇到未标记的东西时
and every time I come across an unmarked thing
我就把它连接到我的自由表里面
I'm going to link it together in my free list.
传统而且非常简单的算法
Classic, very simple algorithm.
我们看
So let's see.
它很简单吗?
Is that very simple?
是的
Yes it is.
我不会深入代码细节
I'm not going to go through the code in any detail,
只是想给你看看它有多长
but I just want to show you about how long it is.
看这个标记阶段
Let's look at the mark phase.
这是标记阶段的第一部分
Here's the first part of the mark phase.
我们找到根
We pick up the root.
我们要
We're going to do some
我们要对它进行递归过程调用
We're going to use that as a recursive procedure call.
当我们完成标记之后
We're going to sweep from there,
就从这里开始清除
after when we're done with marking.
#TBD
And then we're going to do a little couple of instructions that do this checking out on the marks and changing the marks and things like that,
按照我刚才讲的那个算法进行
according to the algorithm I've just shown you.
#TBD
It comes out here.
你需要标记它们的CAR
You have to mark the cars of things
也需要标记它们的CDR
and you also have to be able to mark the cdrs of things.
这就是整个标记阶段
That's the entire mark phase.
我给你讲个关于它的小故事
I'll just tell you a little story about this.
古董货DEC PDP-6计算机
The old DEC PDP-6 computer,
它的标记清除垃圾回收就是这样的
this was the way that the mark-sweep garbage collection, as it was, was written.
程序很短
The program was so small
包括它需要的数据
that with the data that it needed,
还包括它用来操作内存的寄存器
with the registers that it needed to manipulate the memory,
能放到机器的快速寄存器里 #TBD 16
it fit into the fast registers of the machine, which were 16.
整个程序
The whole program.
你可以在快速寄存器里执行指令
And you could execute instructions in the fast registers.
所以这是个非常短的程序
So it's an extremely small program,
它跑得飞快
and it could run very fast.
很不幸
Now unfortunately, of course,
因为这个程序是递归的
this program, because the fact that it's recursive
#TBD
in the way that you do something first and then you do something after that,
你不得不先处理CAR 再处理CDR
you have to work on the cars and then the cdrs,
这需要海量的内存
it requires auxiliary memory.
所以Lisp系统需要一个栈来进行标记
So Lisp systems-- those requires a stack for marking.
Lisp系统通过这样的方式
Lisp systems that are built this way
限制了你在数据结构上
have a limit to the depth of recursion you can have
进行CAR或者CDR递归的深度
in data structures in either the car or the cdr,
这并不太靠谱
and that doesn't work very nicely.
另一方面 当它足够大的时候你不会发现
On the other hand, you never notice it if it's big enough.
例如对于Maclisp#TBD
And that's certainly been the case for most Maclisp, for example,
#TBD
which ran Macsyma where you could deal with expressions of thousands of elements long.
These are algebraic expressions with thousand of terms.
这没什么问题
And there's no problem with that.
垃圾回收器能正常工作
Such, the garbage collector does work.
另一方面
On the other hand,
这个算法有个很精妙的魔改版
there's a very clever modification to this algorithm,
但我不会去讲
which I will not describe,
它是由两个人提出的
by Peter Deutsch and Schorr and Waite--
IBM的Herb Schorr和Waite
Herb Schorr from IBM and Waite,
后者我不认识
who I don't know.
这个算法让你
That algorithm allows you to build--
能够不消耗大量内存就完成工作
you do can do this without auxiliary memory,
通过反转你下降的时候的指针
by remembering as you walk the data structures
#TBD
where you came from by reversing the pointers as you go down
通过反转的指针再回去
and crawling up the reverse pointers as you go up.
这是个很取巧的算法
It's a rather tricky algorithm.
你第一次写它 事实上 前三次你写的时候都会写出惊天大bug
The first time you write it-- or in fact, the first three times you write it it has a terrible bug in it.
也可能跑得奇慢无比
And it's also rather slow,
因为这个算法太复杂了
because it's complicated.
它用了七倍的内存引用
It takes about six times as many memory references
来完成我们刚才讨论的任务
to do the sorts of things that we're talking about.
一旦我完成了标记阶段
Well now once I've done this marking phase,
#TBD
and I get into a position where things look like this, let's look-- yes.
这里完成了标记工作 和我刚才做的一样
Here we have the mark done, just as I did it.
现在我们要进行清除阶段
Now we have to perform the sweep phase.
我刚才已经讲过如何清除了
And I described to you what this sweep is like.
我要从内存的一端开始
I'm going to walk down from one end of memory or the other,
哪一端都可以
I don't care where,
扫描内存中的每个格子
scanning every cell that's in the memory.
在扫描的同时
And as I scan these cells,
如果是空闲内存
I'm going to link them together, if they are free,
就把它们连接到自由表里
into the free list.
如果它们不是空闲内存
And if they're not free,
我就把它们的标记清除掉
I'm going to unmark them so the marks become zero.
事实上
And in fact what I get--
最终的程序并不很复杂
well the program is not very complicated.
它只是变长了一些
It looks sort of like this-- it's a little longer.
这是第一部分
Here's the first piece of it.
它从内存的顶端下降下来
This one's coming down from the top of memory.
我不期望你现在就搞懂它
I don't want you to try to understand this at this point.
它挺简单的
It's rather simple.
这是个非常简单的算法
It's a very simple algorithm,
#TBD
but there's pieces of it that just sort of look like this.
非常显而易见
They're all sort of obvious.
在清理结束后
And after we've done the sweep,
我们就得到了长这个样子的结果
we get an answer that looks like that.
标记清除算法有一些缺点
Now there are some disadvantages with mark-sweep algorithms of this sort.
最严重的一个是
Serious ones.
最重要的缺点是
One important disadvantage is
你的内存越来越大
that your memories get larger and larger.
内存空间越来越大
As you say, address spaces get larger and larger,
你想用它存更多东西
you're willing to represent more and more stuff,
这导致扫描整个内存的耗时特别长
then it gets very costly to scan all of memory.
你真正想做的是只扫描有用的东西
What you'd really like to do is only scan useful stuff.
这样就会好一点
It would even be better
如果你意识到有些东西是有用的
if you realized that some stuff was known to be good and useful,
你就没必要去多次检查它
and you don't have to look at it more than once or twice.
或者不用经常去检查它
Or very rarely.
对于那些你不太确定的
Whereas other stuff that you're not so sure about,
你可以在每次需要的时候
you can look at more detail
进行仔细检查
every time you want to do this,
也就是垃圾回收的时候
want to garbage collect.
这些算法就是用了这样的方法
Well there are algorithms that are organized in this way.
我要介绍一个著名的古老算法
Let me tell you about a famous old algorithm
它让你只检查可用部分的内存
which allows you only look at the part of memory which is known to be useful.
这让它成为了最快的垃圾回收算法
And which happens to be the fastest known garbage collector algorithm.
它就是Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson垃圾回收算法
This is the Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson garbage collector algorithm.
它在1961年或1960年时由Minsky发明
It was invented by Minsky in 1961 or '60 or something,
当时是给RLE PDP-1 Lisp用的
for the RLE PDP-1 Lisp,
这个机器只有4096个字的线性内存
which had 4,096 words of list memory,
还有个磁鼓
and a drum.
#TBD
And the whole idea was to garbage collect this terrible memory.
Minsky发现打成目的最容易的方法是
What Minsky realized was the easiest way to do this
一视同仁地扫描整个内存
is to scan the memory in the same sense,
遍历好的结构
walking the good structure,
把它复制到磁鼓中
copying it out into the drum,
压缩一下
compacted.
之后把它们复制出来
And then when we were done copying it all out,
并把它们交换回内存里
then you swap that back into your memory.
不管你有没有用磁鼓或者其他的内存
Now whether or you not use a drum, or another piece of memory,
这不重要
or something like that isn't important.
事实上
In fact,
我觉得现在应该没人用磁鼓了吧
I don't think people use drums anymore for anything.
但这个算法依赖
But this algorithm basically depends upon having
大约两倍于你实际使用的内存
about twice as much address space as you're actually using.
最开始 你有一些
And so what you have is some, initially,
可用的数据和垃圾的混合物
some mixture of useful data and garbage.
它被成为fromspace
So this is called fromspace.
这是crud的混合
And this is a mixture of crud.
有些是有用的有些没有
Some of it's important and some of it isn't.
有一个地方需要足够大
Now there's another place which is hopefully big enough,
这个地方叫topspace
if we recall, tospace,
要把东西复制进去
which is where we're copying to.
然后就发生了
And what happens is--
我不会深入细节
and I'm not going to go through this detail.
书上写得很清楚了
It's in our book quite explicitly.
有一个你开始的根节点
There's a root point where you start from.
你从这里开始
And the idea is that you start with the root.
复制你看到的第一个东西
You copy the first thing you see,
根指针指向的第一个东西
the first thing that the root points at,
复制到topspace的开始
to the beginning of tospace.
第一个东西是一个序对或者数据结构
The first thing is a pair or something like, a data structure.
然后在那里留下一个破碎的心
You then also leave behind a broken heart saying,
表示我把东西从这移动到这
I moved this object from here to here,
在它要去的地方分配空间
giving the place where it moved to.
叫作破碎的心是因为
This is called a broken heart because
1966年我的一个朋友实现了它
a friend of mine who implemented one of these in 1966
而他是个文艺青年
was a very romantic character
就取名叫破碎的心
and called it a broken heart.
不论如何
But in any case,
接下来要做的是
the next thing you do
这有个新的free pointer
is now you have a new free pointer which is here,
你开始扫描
and you start scanning.
你扫描这个你刚复制过的数据结构
You scan this data structure you just copied.
每当你encounter一个指针到里面
And every time you encounter a pointer in it,
你把它当作根指针
you treat it as if it was the root pointer here.
对不起
Oh, I'm sorry.
你做的另一件事是 你将根指针移动到这里
The other thing you do is you now move the root pointer to there.
所以你可以扫描这里
So now you scan this,
把每个遇到的东西都作为根指针对待
and everything you see you treat as it were the root pointer.
如果你看到了什么
So if you see something,
它指向了这里的某个地方
well it points up into there somewhere.
它指向了你没复制的东西吗?
Is it pointing at a thing which you've not copied yet?
这里有破碎的心吗
Is there a broken heart there?
如果那有破碎的心
If there's a broken heart there
就说明那里有东西被复制了
and it's something you have copied,
#TBD
you've just replaced this pointer with the thing a broken heart points at.
如果它还没被复制
If this thing has not been copied,
你把它复制到这里
you copy it to the next place over here.
把你的free指针移到这里
Move your free pointer over here,
然后在那放个破碎的心
and then leave a broken heart behind
继续扫描
and scan.
最终已扫描的指针追上了free指针
And eventually when the scant pointer hits the free pointer,
内存里的所有东西都被复制了
everything in memory has been copied.
那么就有一大堆空闲空间了
And then there's a whole bunch of empty space up here,
你就可以把它们放进自由表里
which you could either make into a free list, if that's what you want to do.
但通常在这种系统中你不会这样做
But generally you don't in this kind of system.
在这个系统中你顺序分配你的内存
In this system you sequentially allocate your memory.
这是个非常 非常好的算法
That is a very, very nice algorithm,
在你们用的scheme里就有这样的东西
and sort of the one we use in the scheme that you've been using.
它应该是--
And it's expected--
我相信没人能发现比它跑得更快的算法
I believe no one has found a faster algorithm than that.
有一些对这个算法的简单修改
There are very simple modifications to this algorithm
由Henry Baker发明
invented by Henry Baker
它让你能实时运行这个算法
which allow one to run this algorithm in real time,
这意味着你在垃圾回收的时候不需要停下来
meaning you don't have to stop to garbage collect.
你能让机器运行的CONS操作
But you could interleave the consing that the machine does when its running
与垃圾回收过程交错进行
with steps of the garbage collection process,
垃圾回收器是分散式的
so that the garbage
collector's distributed
机器不需要停下来
and the machine doesn't have to stop,
再让垃圾回收开始运作
and garbage collecting can start.
在使用虚拟内存的机器中
Of course in the case of machines with virtual memory
其中有很多无法访问的地方
where a lot of it is in inaccessible places,
会使过程变得十分昂贵
this becomes a very expensive process.
有许多对它进行改进的尝试
And there have been numerous attempts to make this much better.
对于感兴趣的同学 这有一篇论文
There is a nice paper, for those of you who are interested,
由Moon等人写的
by Moon and other people
这篇论文描述了对于insky-Fenichel-Yochelson算法的一种改良办法
which describes a modification to the incremental Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson algorithm,
和Baker算法的一个修改
and modification the Baker algorithm
让使用虚拟内存的系统更加高效
which is more efficient for virtual memory systems.
现在最后一个谜团也解开了
Well I think now the mystery to this is sort of gone.
谁有问题呢
And I'd like to see if there are any questions.
请讲
Yes.
学生: 我在楼上的一些系统里看到你运行的垃圾回收器
AUDIENCE: I saw one of you run the garbage collector on the systems upstairs,
它看起来跑得飞快
and it seemed to me to run extremely fast.
它真的清理了整个内存吗?
Did the whole thing take-- does it sweep through all of memory?
教授: 没有
PROFESSOR: No.
它只清理了那些需要复制有用数据结构的内存
It swept through exactly what was needed to copy the useful structure.
它是个复制收集器
It's a copying collector.
它确实很快#TBD
And it is very fast. On the whole, I suppose to copy--
#TBD
in a Bobcat-- to copy,
一个3MB的东西将在1秒内完成
I think, a three megabyte thing or something is less than a second, real time.
它们是非常小的程序
Really, these are very small programs.
你需要注意到的一件事是
One thing you should realise is that
垃圾回收器必须要小
garbage collectors have to be small.
不是因为它们需要跑得很快
Not because they have to be fast,
而是因为没人能对一个复杂的垃圾回收器排查错误
but because no one can debug a complicated garbage collector.
如果一个垃圾回收器不能正常工作
A garbage collector, if it doesn't work,
它会把你的内存搞得一团糟
will trash your memory in such a way
而你却束手无策
that you cannot figure out what the hell happened.
#TBD
You need an audit trail.
因为它把所有东西都换了位置
Because it rearranges everything,
你又如何知道发生了什么
and how do you know what happened there?
#TBD
So this is the only kind of program that
it really, seriously matters if you stare at it long enough so you believe that it works.
#TBD
And sort of prove it to yourself.
无法对它进行查错
So there's no way to debug it.
这意味着它需要足够小
And that takes it being small enough
让你能脑补出它的工作情况
so you can hold it in your head.
垃圾回收器的就是如此特殊
Garbage collectors are special in this way.
所以每个#TBD的垃圾回收器一定体积很小
So every reasonable garbage collector has gotten small,
而通常小程序跑得就快
and generally small programs are fast.
请提问
Yes.
学生: 您能再重复一遍这个技术的名字吗?
AUDIENCE: Can you repeat the name of this technique once again?
教授: 是Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson垃圾回收器
PROFESSOR: That's the Minsky-Fenichel-Yochelson garbage collector.
学生: 啥?
AUDIENCE: You got that?
教授: Minsky在1961年时为RLE PDP-1发明了它
PROFESSOR: Minsky invented it in '61 for the RLE PDP-1.
它的一个版本被Fenichel和Yochelson继续开发优化后
A version of it was developed and elaborated
被用在了Multics Maclisp里面
to be used in Multics Maclisp by Fenichel and Yochelson
那时大约是1968或者1969年
in somewhere around 1968 or '69.
好
OK.
休息一下
Let's take a break.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
教授: 我们到课程的最后一部分了
PROFESSOR: Well we've come to the end of this subject,
我已经给你们展示了一个通用的机器
and we've already shown you a universal machine
它被简化为求值器
which is down to evaluator.
它被简化到
It's down to the level of detail
你能想象自己可以做一个
you could imagine you could make one.
这就是个特定的Lisp实现
This is a particular implementation of Lisp,
就是用我昨天讲到的
built on one of those
scheme芯片做的
scheme chips that was talked about yesterday,
就是这个
sitting over here.
#TBD
This is mostly interface to somebody's memory
with a little bit of timing and other such stuff.
但它们实际能以合理的速度
But this fellow actually ran Lisp
运行Lisp
at a fairly reasonable rate, as interpretive.
它跑得像1979年的
It ran Lisp as fast as a DEC PDP-10
DEC PDP-10一样快
back in 1979.
这是一个硬件
And so it's gotten pretty hardware.
是个实物
Pretty concrete.
#TBD
We've also downed you a bit with the things you can compute.
那么有我们无法计算的情况吗?
But is it the case that there are things we can't compute?
让我以展示一些
And so I'd like to end this with
你不能计算的东西作为结尾
showing you some things that you'd like be able to compute that you can't.
答案是 是的
The answer is yes,
有无法计算的事物
there are things you can't compute.
例如
For example,
你很想要这样一种东西
something you'd really like is--
当你正在写一个编译器时
if you're writing a compiler
你想要一个程序
you'd like a program that would check
检查你的代码能不能正常运行
that the thing you're going to do will work.
这不是很棒吗?
Wouldn't that be nice?
你希望能够捕获死循环
You'd like something that would catch infinite loops,
例如
for example,
用户的程序里的死循环
in programs that were written by users.
但通常你写不出这样的程序
But in general you can't write such a program
它读取和检测某个程序
that will read any program and determine whether or not
是不是死循环
it's an infinite loop.
我给你展示一下
Let me show you that.
这是个关于数学的小例子
It's a little bit of a minor mathematics.
设想
Let's imagine
在我们开始之前
that we just had a mathematical function
有一个数学函数
before we start.
这里就有一个
And there is one,
称为S
called s,
它接受一个过程
which takes a procedure
和它的参数a
and its argument, a.
S所做的是
And what s does
检测以a为参数运行p时
is it determines whether or not
是否安全
it's safe to run p on a.
我的意思是
And what I mean by that is this:
如果a可以作为p的参数
it's true if p applied to a
最终能返回一个值
to a will converge
就返回true
to a value
在没有报错的情况下
without an error.
但当以a为参数调用p
And it's false
是死循环
if p of a
或者会报错
or makes an error.
就返回false
loops forever
这确实是个函数
Now that's surely a function.
对于你输入的任何过程
There is some for every procedure
或者任何参数
and for every argument you could give it
它只能返回true或false
that is either true or false
不会报错
that it converges without making an error.
你可以为它们画一张巨大的表格
And you could make a giant table of them.
但问题是
But the question is,
你能写个一个过程
can you write a procedure
计算这个函数的值吗?
that compute the values of this function?
假设我们能做到
Well let's assume that we can.
假设
Suppose
我们有个过程
that we have a procedure
叫作SAFE?
procedure called "safe"
它能计算S的值
that computes the value of s.
现在我要用几种方法
Now I'm going to show you by several methods
证明你做不到
that you can't do this.
最简单的一个
The easiest one,
或者说第一个
or the first one,
我们定义一个叫diag1的过程
let's define a procedure called diag1.
#TBD
Given that we have safe,
我们可以定义
we can define diag1
diag1
是有一个参数p
to be the procedure
的过程
of one argument, p,
它有着这样的属性
which has the following properties.
如果它对自己应用p
If it's safe to apply p to itself,
那么就形成了死循环
then I wish to have an infinite loop.
否则我会返回3
Otherwise I'm going to return 3.
它也可能是42
Maybe it was 42.
宇宙的终极答案是什么?
What's the answer to the big question?
我们当然知道死循环是什么
Where of course we know what an infinite loop is.
死循环
Infinite loop,
没有参数的过程
to be a procedure of no arguments,
这是一个极好的lambda运算循环
which is that nice lambda calculus loop.
lambda (x)
Lambda of x,
(X X)
x of x,
应用到(lambda (x) (x x))
applied to lambda of x, x of x.
没什么想象的余地了
So there's nothing left to the imagination here.
总结一下
Well let's see what the story is.
我假设
I'm supposing it's the case
我们担心有个过程
that we worry about the procedure
把diag1应用到diag1上
called diag1 applied to diag1.
那会发生什么呢?
Well what could it possibly be?
我不知道
Well I don't know.
将diag1代换为
We're going to substitute diag1
p的过程体
for p in the body here.
计算(diag1 diag1)安全吗?
Well is it safe to compute diag1 of diag1?
我不知道
I don't know.
有两种可能
There are two possibilities.
如果计算(diag1 diag1)是安全的
If it's safe to compute diag1 of diag1
这意味着不会循环
that means it shouldn't loop.
意味着我到了这里
That means I go to here,
然后我生成了个死循环
but then I produce an infinite loop.
所以它不是安全的
So it can't be safe.
但如果计算(diag1 diag1)不安全
But if it's not safe to compute diag1 of diag1
那么它的结果是3
then the answer to this is 3.
但那是(diag1 diag1)
But that's diag1 of diag1,
所以它必须安全才行
so it had to be safe.
由于这个矛盾
So therefore by contradiction
你无法写出这个SAFE?过程
you cannot produce safe.
对于没听懂这个叙述的同学
For those of you who were boggled by that one
我换个方式再讲一遍
I'm going to say it again, in a different way.
请听另一个版本
Listen to one more alternative.
我们定义diag2
Let's define diag2.
这个diag的名字
These are named diag because
来源于康托尔的对角论证法
of Cantor's diagonal argument.
#TBD
These are instances of
a famous argument which was originally used by
Cantor在19世纪末
Cantor in the late part of the last century
证明了实数是无限的
to prove that the real numbers were not countable,
用整数无法数完实数
that there are too many real numbers to be counted by integers.
举例来说
That there are more points on a line,
在数轴上
for example,
点的数量比计数的数字多
than there are counting numbers.
直线上的点比自然数多
这或许不是个显而易见的结论
It may or may not be obvious,
但我不想深入讨论这个
and I don't want to get into that now.
但是diag2
But diag2
仍有一个参数的过程p
is again a procedure of one argument p.
这几乎与之前的例子相同
It's almost the same as the previous one,
如果计算(p p)是安全的
which is, if it's safe to compute p on p,
那么我就要
then I'm going to produce--
要去计算
then I want to compute
一些(p p)之外的
some other things
其他东西
other than p of p.
否则我就返回false
Otherwise I'm going to put out false.
这里的other-than意思是
Where other then it says,
不管这个(p p)是什么
whatever p of p,
我都返回一些别的东西
I'm going to put out something else.
我会告诉你
I can give you an example of
一个other-than的定义
a definition of other than
我觉得它是可用的
which I think works.
我们看
Let's see.
是的
Yes.
定义other-than
Where other than
是一个以x为参数的过程
be a procedure of one argument x which says,
如果x等于'A
if its eq x to, say, quote a,
那么结果是'B
then the answer is quote b.
否则结果是'A
Otherwise it's quote a.
这就能做到不管参数是什么
That always produces something
我都能给出与参数不同的结果
which is not what its argument is.
就是这样
That's all it is.
这就是我要的
That's all I wanted.
我们考虑一下这个
Well now let's consider this one,
(diag2 diag2)
diag2 of diag2.
看
Well look.
这个东西会做些危险的事情
This only does something dangerous,
比如求值(p p)
like calling p of p,
如果它是是安全的
if it's safe to do so.
如果SAFE?能够被定义的话
So if safe defined at all,
如果你能定义SAFE?过程
if you can define such a procedure, safe,
那么这个过程
then this procedure
总是安全的
is always defined and therefore safe
对于任意输入来说都是
on any inputs.
那么(diag2 diag2)
So diag2 of diag2
一定会返回(diag2 diag2)以外的东西
must reduce to other than diag2 of diag2.
这就没意义了
And that doesn't make sense,
又产生了悖论
so we have a contradiction,
因此我们不能定义SAFE?
and therefore we can't define safe.
我只想这样证明两次
I just waned to do that twice,
有些许不同
slightly differently,
你不会感到
so you wouldn't feel
第一个证明是个把戏
that the first one was a trick.
他们都是小把戏
They may be both tricks,
但它们稍微有些不同
but they're at least slightly different.
#TBD
So I suppose that pretty much wraps it up.
我们刚刚论证了停机问题
I've just proved what we call the halting theorem,
#TBD
and I suppose with that we're going to halt.
I hope you have a good time.
有什么问题吗?
Are there any questions?
请讲
Yes.
学生: diag1的值是什么?
AUDIENCE: What is the value of s of diag1?
教授: 什么的值?
PROFESSOR: Of what?
学生: (S diag1)的值
AUDIENCE: S of diag1.
如果你说S是个函数
If you said s is a function
我们可以
and we can [INTERPOSING VOICES]
教授: 噢 我不知道啊
PROFESSOR: Oh, I don't know.
我不知道
I don't know.
它是一个函数
It's a function,
但我不知道如何计算它
but I don't know how to compute it.
我做不到
I can't do it.
我也只是个机器
I'm just a machine, too.
对吧?
Right?
原则上来说
There's no machine
没有机器
that in principle--
会处在你刚才问的那个情况中
it might be that in that particular case you just asked,
#TBD
with some thinking I could figure it out.
但通常情况下
But in general
我无法计算S的值
I can't compute the value of s
别的机器也做不到
any better than any other machine can.
存在这样一个函数
There is such a function,
没有任何机器能够计算它
it's just that no machine can be built to compute it.
现在
Now
#TBD
there's a way of saying that that should not be surprising.
Going through this--
我并没有时间在这展示这个
I mean, I don't have time to do this here,
但这样的函数非常多
but the number of functions is very large.
如果有一定量的可能输入
If there's a certain number of answers possible
和结果
and a certain number of inputs possible,
那么结果对应输入的数量
then it's the number of answers raised to the number inputs
就是可能函数的数量
is the number of possible functions.
对于同一个参数来说
On one variable.
#TBD
Now that's always bigger than the thing you're raising to, the exponent.
函数的数量
The number of functions is larger
比一个人能写出的
than the number of programs
程序的数量更多
that one can write,
因为有无穷多的参数
by an infinity counting argument.
可能会更多
And it's much larger.
所以不可计算的函数数量
So there must be a lot of functions
一定会非常多
that can't be computed by programs.
学生: 不久前
AUDIENCE: A few moments ago
你讲了规范
you were talking about specifications
和自动生成解决方案
and automatic generation of solutions.
你觉得在规范和解决方案之间存在#TBD吗?
Do you see any steps between specifications and solutions?
教授: 存在的
PROFESSOR: Steps between.
你是说
You mean, you're saying,
如何按照规范
how you go about constructing
构建相应的装置吗?
devices given that have specifications for the device?
是的
Sure.
学生: 软件工程中有很多
AUDIENCE: There's a lot of software engineering
层次化的设计
that goes through specifications through
并进行实现的规范
many layers of design and then implementation.
教授: 是的
PROFESSOR: Yes?
学生: 我很好奇
AUDIENCE: I was curious
你觉得这现实吗?
if you think that's realistic.
教授: 我觉得其中一些是现实的
PROFESSOR: Well I think that some of it's realistic
另一些不现实
and some of it isn't.
如果你想制造一个滤波器
I mean, surely if I want to build an electrical filter
我这有个挺有趣的例子
and I have a rather interesting possibility.
假设我想制造一个东西
Supposing I want to build a thing that matches
无线电广播发射机
some power output to the radio transmitter,
到某些天线
to some antenna.
#TBD
And I'm really out of this power-- it's output tube out here.
问题是它们的阻抗不同
And the problem is that they have different impedances.
我希望能够匹配阻抗
I want them to match the impedances.
我也想制造一个滤波器
I also want to make a filter
用来过滤一些谐波辐射
in there which is going to get rid of some harmonic radiation.
一个老派的技术叫作
Well one old-fashioned technique for doing this is called
镜像阻抗或之类的东西
image impedances, or something like that.
你要做的是
And what you do
你有个基础的模块
is you say you have a basic module
称为L型滤波器
called an L-section.
就像这样
Looks like this.
如果把它连接到某些电阻R上
If I happen to connect this to some resistance, r,
#TBD
and if I make this impedance x, xl,
and if it happens to be q times r,
这就成了一个低通滤波器
then this produces a low pass filter
有q^2+1的阻抗匹配
with a q square plus one impedance match.
这就是我想要的
Just what I need.
因为这样我就可以
Because now I can take two of these,
把它们匹配到一起了
hook them together
就像这样
like this.
我拿来另一个
OK, and I take another one
想这样把它们连到一起
and I'll hook them together like that.
有两个L型滤波器连接起来
And I have two L-sections hooked together.
这能让它的阻抗降到我知道的值
And this will step the impedance down to one that I know,
让它的阻抗升到我知道的值
and this will step it up to one I know.
这两个低通滤波器都过滤掉了一些谐波
Each of these is a low pass filter getting rid of some harmonics.
这是个不错的滤波器
It's good filter,
它成为π型滤波器
it's called a pie-section filter.
很好
Great.
除了实际上
Except for the fact that in doing what I just did,
我在系统里放了些无用的东西
I've made a terrible inefficiency in this system.
我在本该一个线圈的地方用了两个
I've made two coils where I should have made one.
在大多数软件工程中
And the problem with most software engineering art
在人工优化和编译之外
is that there's no mechanism,
不存在一种机制
other than people optimization and compilers,
能在自顶向下的设计中
for getting rid of the redundant parts
去掉冗余的部分
that are constructed when doing top down design.
或许会更糟
It's even worse,
有很多重要的结构
there are lots of very important structures
你无法采用这种方式构建
that you can't construct at all this way.
我觉得自上而下的设计方式
So I think that the standard top down design
是一种很短视的手段
is a rather shallow business.
它不会真的抓到
Doesn't really capture
设计者真正想要的结果
what people want to do in design.
我再举一个电子学的例子
I'll give you another electrical example.
电子学的例子
Electrical examples are so much clearer
要比计算的例子直观得多
than computational examples,
因为计算的例子
because computation examples require
解释起来比较复杂
a certain degree of complexity to explain them.
电子学世界中 我最喜欢的例子之一是
But one of my favorite examples in the electrical world
是如何设计中频放大器中
is how would I ever come up with the output stage
输入级和输出级的连接方式
of this inter-stage connection in an IF amplifier.
这是一个三极管
It's a little transistor here, and let's see.
这有个LC震荡电路
Well I'm going to have a tank,
我要把它
and I'm going to hook this up to, say,
把它与下一级的输入线圈耦合在一起
I'm going to link-couple that to the input of the next stage.
这是个完美的可行方案
Here's a perfectly plausible plan--
除了我这个电流方向画错了
well except for the fact that since I put that going up
电流应该是这个方向
I should make that going that way.
这是个完美的可行方案
Here's a perfectly plausible plan for a--
不对
no I shouldn't.
我犯蠢了
I'm dumb.
对不起
Excuse me.
这不重要
Doesn't matter.
关键在于这是一个
The point is it's a perfect
把两级耦合起来的完美方案
plan for a couple two stages together.
分层来看时会产生什么问题?
Now what the problem is is what's this hierarchically?
#TBD
It's not one thing.
当分层来看时它就没有任何意义了
Hierarchically it doesn't make any sense at all.
这是一个调谐电路的电感
It's the inductance of a tuned circuit,
这是变压器的初级线圈
it's the primary of a transformer,
这是直流的通路
and it's also the DC path by
它是三极管的集电极
which bias conditions get to the
的偏置条件
collector of that transistor.
没有任何简单的自顶向下设计
And there's no simple top-down design
能够得到这样的结构
that's going to produce a structure like that
对于同一个东西有大量的复用
with so many overlapping uses for a particular thing.
玩拼字游戏
Playing Scrabble,
当你要完成三倍分数的词时
where you have to do triple word scores,
自顶向下的设计策略并不容易
or whatever, is not so easy in top-down design strategy.
真正的工程基于努力成果的吸引力#TBD
Yet most of real engineering is based on getting the most oomph for effort.
那就是你所看到的东西
And that's what you're seeing here.
嗯?
Yeah?
学生: 这是最后一个问题吗?
AUDIENCE: Is this the last question?
[笑声]
[LAUGHTER]
教授: 看起来是
PROFESSOR: Apparently so.
谢谢大家
Thank you.
[掌声]
[APPLAUSE]
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]